Guide to the Jacques Hnizdovsky Collection
Yale University Arts Library
Jacques Hnizdovsky collection
1944-1987
1970-1985
AOB 61
Yale University Arts Library
1.5
(4 boxes)
This small collection contains primarily examples of the bold graphic style Hnizdovsky adopted toward the end of his career in the 1970s and 1980s. Some of the prints are hand colored; many are signed editions.
Hnizdovsky, Jacques, 1915-1985
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the artist, 1980, 1981, 1983. Gift of Stephania Hnizdovsky, 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Jacques Hnizdovsky, a Ukrainian-American woodcut artist, was born in the Ukraine in 1915. He was a student at the Academy of Fine Arts in Warsaw in 1939 when the Nazis invaded Poland. He made his way to the Academy of Fine Arts in Zagreb, Yugoslavia, and made his living as a freelance graphic designer. He painted and, in the early 1940s, did some woodcut work. One of his freelance jobs took him to Paris and, ultimately in 1949, to the U.S. Hnizdovsky started out in St. Paul, MN, and then moved to New York City, where he designed book jackets, posters, fabrics, illustrated books, and other jobs that allowed him to continue his painting and woodblock printmaking. He died in 1985.
Scope and Contents
This small collection contains primarily examples of the bold graphic style Hnizdovsky adopted toward the end of his career in the 1970s and 1980s. Some of the prints are hand colored; many are signed editions.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series: I. Bookplates. II. Drawings. III. Proofs. IV. Prints. V. Posters. VI. Woodblocks. VII. Biographical Materials and Small Designs.
Wood-engraving; Prints -- 20th Century; Illustration of books; Wood blocks (printing blocks); Drawings (visual works)
- Bookplates, Series I
  - Academiæ Scientiarum Ucrainensis Liberæ, 1947; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ex Libris [IZ?], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Harvard College Ukranian Seminar, 1972 undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - HN [Hnizdovsky], 1972; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Fanny Hnizdovsky, 1982 1983; 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jacques Hnizdovsky, 1982; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sylvie Stoyanka Junod, 1982; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Marian S. Kouzan, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ada Kulyk, 1977; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pamela Wick Lincoln, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ken Mitchell, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mt. San Angelo, 1983; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Miroslav Prokop], 1974; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nina Severin, 1972; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - William Smart, 1983; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sonja Haussman Smith, 1982; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - William Jay Smith, 1982; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rostyslav Sonevytsky, 1975; 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jean Thiebault, 1947; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gil Williams, 1973; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bookplates from Ex Libris [1986 accession]
    - XVII Congresso Internazionale Dell'Ex Libris Lugano 1978, 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Academiæ Scientiarum Ucrainensis Liberæ, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [AR], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Audrey Spencer Arellanes, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - William Elliott Butler, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Achilles Chreptowsky, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ex Libris [IZ?], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Roman Ferencevych, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Genya & Ihor Galarnyk, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Richard Gasperi, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Golian], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - H, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Harvard College Library, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Harvard College Ukrainian Seminar, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Hevryk], undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [HN], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fanny Hnizdovsky, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jacques Hnizdovsky, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mary-Martha Hnizdovsky, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Nadi & Anton Ivakhniuk], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Benoît Junod, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Sylvie Stoyanka Junod, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Eaghoris Kostetzky, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Familæ Kravciv, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ada Kulyk, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Olga Kuzmovich], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pamela Wick Lincoln, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ken Mitchell, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mt. San Angelo, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Miroslav Prokop], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Nina Severin, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - William Smart, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Sonja Haussmann Smith, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - William Jay Smith, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - E. B. Smyk, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rostyslav Sonevytsky, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Danyl Struk, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Sweet Briar College, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dr. Joseph Szandra, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jean Thiebault, 1947; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - James L. Weil, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [WHM], undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gil Williams, 1973 1976; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified, 1947 undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Additional Bookplates
    - H, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Mary-Martha Hnizdovsky, undated 1972; 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Benoît Junod, 1982; 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Pamela Wick Lincoln, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Drawings, Series II
  - [Winged tree], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Swan with Keats's name in water], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Apple and walnut drawings], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Apple and walnut proofs with drawing on top], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Tree drawing], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Flower drawing], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - PART SIX [violet primrose], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - PART THREE Soneto 1816-1818 [Keats project, spider web], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - PART TREE [sic] Soneto 1816-1818 [Keats project, grasshopper], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - JOHN KEATS first sketches submitted - J. H. [sketches for text for Keats project], 1964; 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    General note
    Includes mock-ups for a book jacket design, title page, and headpiece.
- Proofs, Series III
  - [Duck], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kivi, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Helianthus (Sunflower), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hyacinthus, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Geoganthus, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Plant], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Potted plant], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Yucca, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Iris, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Winged tree], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Willow, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Apple], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Walnut], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Apple Tree, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Illustration to "Poems of John Keats" [thistles], 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Illustration to "Poems of John Keats" [doors], 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Nude male figure encircled by flames], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes note: "First sketch for the jacket which was actually used."
  - Eudymion, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes note: "intended illustration for John Keats not used, woodblock destroyed."
  - [Snakes], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes note: "Finally I have decided not to use this as the illustration. The woodblock has been destroyed."
  - [Ram profile], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Gratitude], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Design includes the following quote: "There is no more pleasing exercise of the mind than gratitude."
  - Marguerites, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Owl], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Herd of Sheep, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dandelion, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Old Tree, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Simon [black cat], 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Cat, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sleeping Cat, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ram Profile, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Prints, Series IV
  - The Cathedral's Columbarium [pamphlet], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Telephone Booths, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adam's Needle, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Poplar Trees, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jacobin Pigeon, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bush, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Apples in a Basket, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Doors, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Windows, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes note: "intended, but not used as illustration to J. Keats."
  - Eudymion, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes note: "This version have [sic] not been used on the jacket for Poems of John Keats. Instead the sketch (also in wood) for this woodcut has been used on the jacket."
  - Caged Eagle, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes note: "From the 'Poems of John Keats.'"
  - Onion, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Castle in the Sky, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Circle of Growth, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Albatross, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Winged Tree, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hooded Merganser, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Red Cabbage, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ram, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Japanese Chrysanthemum, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - St. John the Divine, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Head of bearded man], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Harkness Tower, Yale University], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Praying Child, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miser, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Posters, Series V
  - Jacques Hnizdovsky: Oils, Woodcuts and Drawings: May 27-June 18, 1978, The Museum of the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, Amsterdam at 112th St., New York City (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Woodcuts by Jacques Hnizdovsky, February 12-March 3, 1978, Newcomb Hall & Alderman Library, University of Virginia in Charlottesville, 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hnizdovsky: Woodcuts of the Seventies, February 3–March 3 1979, Associated American Artists, 663 Fifth Avenue, New York City (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hnizdovsky: October 24 - November 3, 1980, Newcomb Hall, University of Virginia in Charlottesville (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jacques Hnizdovsky, University of Virginia in Charlottesville, Newcomb Hall, September 12-October 2, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brooklyn Botanic Garden (4 different designs), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes "Early Tulips," "Sunflower," "Lilies," and "Moses in a Boat."
  - Harkness Tower, Yale University, undated (Folder 1)
- Woodblocks, Series VI
  - Harkness Tower, 1977 (Box 2)
  - [Unidentified], 1981 (Box 2)
  - Pollution, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Jap. Chrys., 1981 (Box 2)
  - Rosa, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Tulips, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Irish Setter, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Crocus, 1981 (Box 2)
  - [Nude women and man in flames], undated (Box 2)
  - Cut Down, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Asparagus Ferns, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Thomas Hardy Portrait, 1981 (Box 2)
  - [Winged Tree], undated (Box 2)
  - Ram Profile, 1969 (Box 4)
- Biographical Materials and Small Designs, Series VII
  - Articles on Hnizdovsky, 1976 undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Solo exhibition announcements and catalogs, 1960-1986; 27 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Group shows, 1962-1981; 12 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sales announcements, undated; 7 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Stationery employing Hnizdovsky images, 1963-1973 undated; 14 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera employing Hnizdovsky images, 1974-1987 undated; 11 (Box 3, Folder 13)